Stable Gallery
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Stable Gallery records
1916-1999, bulk 1953-1970
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Stable Gallery
2.8 linear feet
The Stable Gallery records measure 2.8 linear feet and are dated 1916-1999, with the bulk of the collection created between 1953 and 1970, the operating years of the gallery. The gallery was known for its representation of the New York School. Records consist mainly of artist files containing biographical notes, correspondence, price lists, sales and payment information, printed matter, and photographs. A small number of administrative and financial records of the gallery are included, along with printed matter, photographs, and personal papers and estate records of gallery founder and owner Eleanor Ward. Over the years, Stable Gallery presented the first one-man shows of Robert Indiana, Cy Twombly, and Andy Warhol. Among the artists closely associated with the gallery were Joseph Cornell, Edward Dugmore, John Ferren, Alex Katz, Conrad Marca-Relli, Marisol, Joan Mitchell, Isamu Noguchi, Richard Stankiewicz, Cy Twombly, Jack Tworkov, and Wilfred Zogbaum.
Historical Note
Established in 1953 by Eleanor Ward (1911-1984), the Stable Gallery derived its name from its first home, a former livery stable on Seventh Avenue at West 58th Street, New York City. Long interested in art and recognized for her "good taste" and "flair," Mrs. Ward had vaguely considered the idea of opening her own gallery for some time and received encouragement from Christian Dior with whom she had worked in Paris. In 1952, opportunity arose to lease a suitable building that would later become a gallery. At first, Ward and a friend sold mannequins and made the large, empty space available for fashion photography; in December, she operated a Christmas boutique for a few weeks.
Stable Gallery opened in 1953 with an exhibition of work by Ward's friend Mike Mishke, a commercial artist. She then arranged for Stable Gallery to host a sequel to the 1951 Ninth Street Show (the initial show, organized by the Club with financial assistance from Leo Castelli, was held in an empty store on Ninth Street). The New York Artists Annual, better known as the Stable Annual, was selected by the artists themselves; this well-attended, widely-reviewed, and influential exhibition continued until 1957. Participating artists included Philip Guston, Franz Kline, Willem deKooning, Robert Motherwell, Jackson Pollock, Robert Rauschenberg, Ad Reinhardt, Richard Stankiewicz, and Jack Tworkov.
Stable Gallery soon became a gathering place for artists, including some not in Stable's "stable". Over the years, Stable Gallery presented the first one-man shows of Robert Indiana, Cy Twombly, and Andy Warhol. Among the artists closely associated with the gallery were: Joseph Cornell, Edward Dugmore, John Ferren, Alex Katz, Conrad Marca-Relli, Marisol, Joan Mitchell, Isamu Noguchi, Richard Stankiewicz, Cy Twombly, Jack Tworkov, and Wilfred Zogbaum. The gallery was known for dramatic, somewhat theatrical installations, and occasionally presented exhibitions beyond its usual focus (photographs by Hans Namuth and pre-Columbian sculpture, which personally interested Ward.)
When the block where Stable Gallery stood was razed in 1960 to make way for a high rise apartment building, Mrs. Ward moved her gallery to 33 East 74th Street, where she was able to maintain an apartment for herself upstairs. Quite abruptly, Ward closed Stable Gallery in 1970, noting changes in the art scene, growing commercialization, and a loss of enthusiasm that made the gallery merely a business for her. Alan Groh (1923-1996), who started as Eleanor Ward's assistant in 1956 and was eventually named gallery director, became director of A. M. Sachs Gallery. Mrs. Ward traveled widely and acted as an art consultant to selected clients.
Scope and Content Note
The Stable Gallery records measure 2.8 linear feet and are dated 1916-1999 (bulk 1953-1970). Items created earlier than Stable Gallery's establishment or after its closing are printed matter and personal papers of Eleanor Ward.
The Stable Gallery records consist mainly of artist files (Series 1) that contain biographical notes, correspondence, price lists, printed matter, and photographs of art work and artists. The correspondence includes memoranda regarding payments to artists and sales information; among the printed matter is documentation of Stable Gallery and other exhibitions, reviews, and miscellaneous articles. Although the collection contains a small amount of general administrative and financial records (Series 2) and printed matter (Series 3), most Stable Gallery administrative and financial information, as well as related printed matter is included with the artist files. Unfortunately, no records about the famous Stable Annuals held between 1953 and 1957 survive.
Among the miscellaneous items (Series 4) are a small number of Eleanor Ward's personal papers and records concerning her estate. Also included are an audio tape of Ward reminiscing about the Stable Gallery, circa 1970; a transcript of the oral history interview conducted for the Archives of American Art in 1972; a history of Stable Gallery with personal reminiscences written in 1971 by Alan Groh, Ward's assistant from 1956-1970; a videotape of the 1973 Sotheby Parke Bernet auction of selections from the Robert C. Scull collection; and 4 sketch books/pads and loose sheets with charcoal drawings by unidentified artist(s). Photographs (Series 5) are of art work and exhibition installations; Eleanor Ward, friends and family, and numerous parties; and the interior and exterior of Ward's Connecticut house.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series:
Series 1: Artist Files, 1953-1997, undated (Boxes 1-2; 1.75 linear ft.; Reels 5821-5823)
Series 2: Administrative and Financial Records, 1956-1970, and undated (Box 2; 3 folders; Reel 5823)
Series 3: Printed Matter, 1916-1999, undated (Boxes 2-3; 0.25 linear ft.; Reel 5823)
Series 4: Art Work, undated (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet; Reel 5823)
Series 5: Miscellaneous, 1964-1986, undated (Box 4; 0.25 linear ft.; Reel 5823)
Series 6: Photographs, 1955-1983, undated (Box 4; 0.25 linear ft.; Reel 5823)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms.
Subjects:
Anderson, Jeremy, 1921-; Borgrave, Elie; Briggs, Ernest, 1923; Brooks, James, 1906-; Brustlein, Daniel, 1904-; Bultman, Fritz, 1919-1985; Burlin, Paul, 1886-1969; Burri, Alberto, 1915-; Carone, Nicholas, 1917-; Cavallon, Giorgio, 1904-; Cornell, Joseph; De Kooning, Elaine; De Kooning, Willem, 1904-; Dugmore, Edward, 1915-; Ernesto; Ferren, John, 1905-1970; Fiore, Joseph A., 1925-; Goodnough, Robert, 1917-; Indiana, Robert, 1928-; Katz, Alex, 1927-; Krasner, Lee, 1908-; Marca-Relli, Conrad, 1913-; Marisol, 1930-; Mitchell, Fred, 1923-; Mitchell, Joan, 1926-; Morris, Kyle; Motherwell, Robert; Nesbitt, Lowell, 1933-; Noguchi, Isamu, 1904-; Ortman, George, 1926-; Reynal, Jeanne, 1903-; Stankiewicz, Richard, 1922-; Twombly, Cy, 1928-; Tworkov, Jack; Zarnatu, Henrique; Zogbaum, Wilfrid, 1915-1965; Ward, Eleanor, 1912-1984; Scull, Robert, 1917-1986 -- Art collections
Subjects-Topical:
Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Exhibitions; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State) -- New York; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Artists -- United States
Types of Materials:
Sound recordings; Photographs; Sketchbooks
Names:
Groh, Alan, 1923-1996; Ward, Eleanor, 1912-1984
Provenance
The Stable Gallery records were the gift of the Estate of Eleanor Ward. In 1984, artist files were received from Alan Groh, executor of Ward's estate and her assistant at the Stable Gallery. Additional records were donated in 1997 by Buzz Miller on behalf of the Estate of Eleanor Ward; Mr. Miller was Alan Groh's partner and executor of his estate. A final addition was received in 1999 from Paul Gardner, executor of the Estate of Buzz Miller.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm reels 5821-5823. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Artist Files, 1953-1997, undated, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.75 linear feet; Reels 5821-5823)
  Artist files contain various combinations of biographical notes, correspondence (including memoranda regarding payments to artists and sales information), price lists, printed matter, and photographs of art work. Other types of records, photographs of artists and other subjects, and negatives are noted in the folder listing. There are no files for some artists (e.g. Louise Bourgeois, Hans Namuth, Robert Rauschenberg, Jon Schueler) who are known to have exhibited with the gallery. A few of the artists for whom files exist may not have been associated with the Stable Gallery, but perhaps were of interest as potential gallery artists or for Ward's private collection. In a small number of instances, material post-dating the closing of Stable Gallery has been added.
  - Anderson, Jeremy R., 1954-1957 (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Biala, Janice, 1970, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Birmelin, Robert, 1963-1967, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Boghosian, Varujan, 1963-1965, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Borgrave, Elie, 1955-1960, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Briggs, Ernest, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Brooks, James, 1957, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Brustlein, Daniel, 1962, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Bultman, Fritz, 1954-1958, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Burlin, Paul, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Burri, Alberto, 1953-1957, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Cage, John, 1958 (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Carone, Nicholas, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Cavallon, Giorgio, 1954-1960, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Chase, Janet, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Cornell, Joseph, 1954-1968, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Cox, Jan, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - de Kooning, Elaine, 1955-1956, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Diebenkorn, Richard, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Downing, Thomas, 1963-1965, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Dugmore, Edward (includes photograph of the artist), 1953-1958, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Escobar, Marisol (See: Marisol) (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Engman, Robert, 1960-1963, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Ernesto (includes photograph of the artist), 1957 (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Ferren, John (includes photograph of the artist), 1954-1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Fiore, Joe, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Garrigues, Ron, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Goodnough, Robert (includes photograph of the artist), undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Graham, John D., 1961 (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Heller, Dorothy, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Hyde, Solomon, undated (Box 1, Reel 5821)
  - Indiana, Robert (includes writings and notes), 1962-1968, undated, (8 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5821-5822)
  - Insley, Robert, 1968, undated (Box 1, Reel 5822)
  - Katz, Alex (includes photograph of the artist), 1960-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5822)
  - Krasner, Lee, undated (Box 1, Reel 5822)
  - Loew, Michael, undated (Box 1, Reel 5822)
  - Marca-Relli, Conrad, 1954-1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5822)
  - Marisol, 1961-1965, undated (Box 2, Reel 5822)
  - Mitchell, Fred, 1955-1957, undated (Box 2, Reel 5822)
  - Mitchell, Joan (includes photograph of the artist), 1954-1967, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5822)
  - Morris, Kyle, 1956-1958, undated (Box 2, Reel 5822-5823)
  - Motherwell, Robert, 1955, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Nesbitt, Lowell, 1967, 1970, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Noguchi, Isamu, 1954-1961, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Opper, John, 1961, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Ortman, George, 1957-1961, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Pace, Stephen, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Plate, Walter, 1956-1959, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Reynal, Jeanne (includes photographs of Jain temple, the artist, and exhibition installation), 1956-1957, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Sihvonen, Oli, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Stankiewicz, Richard, 1959-1969, 1982, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Thek, Paul, 1970, 1990, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Twombly, Cy (includes photograph of the artist), 1953-1958, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Tworkov, Jack, 1957-1961, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Warhol, Andy, 1962-1997, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Welliver, Neil, 1962-1964, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Zakanych (a.k.a. Zakanitch), Robert, 1968, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Zanartu, Henrique, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Zogbaum, Wilfred, 1957-1961, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
- Administrative and Financial Records, 1956-1970, undated, Series 2:; (Box 2; 3 folders; Reel 5823)
  This series consists of miscellaneous administrative correspondence and financial records of a general nature, or ones concerning multiple artists. Financial material includes banking and investment records, miscellaneous sales, and invoices. Correspondence, sales information, and summaries of payments relating to specific artists are included with Series 1: Artist Files.
  - Financial Records (banking, investments, miscellaneous sales, and invoices), 1956-1971, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1961-1970 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Lists, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
- Printed Matter, 1916-1999, undated, Series 3:; (Boxes 2-3; 0.25 linear feet; Reel 5823)
  This series consists of miscellaneous books, exhibition catalogs, and clippings. Items specifically relating to Eleanor Ward and the Stable Gallery have been microfilmed. These include clippings about Eleanor Ward's New York apartment and her house in Connecticut. Also included are two exhibition catalogs, A Contemporary Collection of Painting and Sculpture Selected from the Collection of Eleanor Ward, Lyman Allen Museum, 1965, and In Honor of Alan Groh '49: The Buzz Miller Collection of American Art, Bayley Art Museum, University of Virginia, 1999 (the collection was acquired mainly from Stable Gallery and donated in honor of Alan Groh, Ward's close friend and long-time assistant). Printed matter relating to Stable Gallery - exhibition, announcements, invitations, reviews, and advertisements - is arranged by artist and included with Series 1: Artist Files.
  - Books, (5 volumes, 2 inscribed; not microfilmed) (Box 2, Reel 5823)
    - Odette: A Fairy Tale for Weary People by Ronald Firbank, 1916 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
    - Poésies by Paul Valéry, 1943 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
    - Bruno Caruso by Leonard Sinisgalli (see Box 3), 1954 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
    - Fishtiary, poems by Michael Braude, drawings by Ralph Carpentier, 1978 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
    - The Bel Canto Pet, undated (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Clippings, 1958-1988, undated, (5 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5823)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (Not Stable Gallery), 1965-1999 (Box 2, Reel 5823)
- Art Work, undated, Series 4:; (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet, Reel 5823)
  Unless otherwise noted, drawings by unidentified artist(s) are in charcoal.
  - Drawings, Vol. 1, 2, 3 (includes some loose drawings), undated (Box 3 (sol), Reel 5823)
  - Drawings (loose sheets; includes a few ballpoint pen drawings), undated (Box 3 (sol), Reel 5823)
- Miscellaneous, 1964-1986, undated, Series 5:; (Box 4; 0.5 linear feet, Reel 5823)
  - Audio/Video Materials (not microfilmed; includes audiocassette of Eleanor Ward reminiscing about Stable Gallery, circa 1970, and videotape of Scull collection auctioned at Sotheby Parke Bernet, 1973), 1973, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - Transcript, Eleanor Ward interviewed by Paul Cummings for the Archives of American Art, Feb. 8, 1972 (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - Stable Gallery History/Reminiscences by Alan Groh (with Groh's résumé), 1971 (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - Eleanor Ward, Estate of (will, financial records, personal and art inventories), 1982-1986, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - Eleanor Ward's Personal Papers, 1964-1983, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Correspondence (includes letters from Ad Reinhardt) (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Financial records (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - "Barn House" floor plan (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Ward's cigarette holder (not microfilmed) (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
- Photographs, 1955-1983, undated, Series 6:; (Box 4; 0.25 linear feet; Reel 5823)
  - Art Work (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Pre-Columbian Sculpture from the Eleanor Ward Collection, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Still Life with Eleanor as Eleanor of France, drawing by Josef Levi (with photocopies of art historical references), circa 1980 (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Unidentified Paintings, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Unidentified Sculpture, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - Exhibition Installations (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Graham Foundation Exhibition at Stable Gallery, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Unidentified Exhibitions, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - People (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Eleanor Ward, 1955-1980, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Eleanor Ward with Others (with Christian Dior, Alan Groh, Buzz Miller, and unidentified), 1960s, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Family [?] (great nephew Toby Ferguson, and unidentified), 1967, 1979, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Alan Groh, Buzz Miller, and Unidentified, 1963, 1965, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Groups (mainly parties, some at Ward's home; few individuals are identified), 1983, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - Places (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Ward's Connecticut Summer House (exterior views), circa 1960 (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Ward's "Barn House," Exterior Views, 1973, 1976, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Ward's "Barn House," Interior views, 1980, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
    - Unidentified Buildings (interior and exterior views), 1979, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects, 1965, 1971, undated (Box 4 (hol), Reel 5823)